WITCH : Come , children , and listen ,
for the story I tell holds a lesson .
A lesson that might one day keep you safe .
So , gather in close and hear me well .
It 's the story of the Beautiful Child
with the little pink cap .
Her birth was a gift to her mother and father
in a time of great suffering and famine .
All in the village agreed
she was the most beautiful child .
But an illness fell upon her ,
and it was predicted
that her first winter would be her last .
Her father was not one to take such tidings passively ,
and whispers told of an enchantress
with the power to cure any ailment .
All that was required was for her father to be brave
and to trust the darkness .
And he was ,
and he did .
But when that enchantress took away the illness ,
she left in its place a gift .
It came to be that the child had been granted Second Sight .
Everyone thought they wanted her to read their futures ,
but then no one wanted to hear what she saw .
For it is only the bitter end
that comes for everyone , anyway .
And she herself made sure of that .
For it was soon clear ...
( HORSE GROANS )
that she was powerful in other ways , too .
( METAL CLANGING )
It seemed she would spare no one .
Not even her own father ,
who , for her , had sacrificed so much .
( HORSE WHINNIES )
And so , it was ordered
that the child be returned to the darkness that made her .
She was hidden away , deep in the woods ,
all alone ,
with no one to play with .
But still , she had her own way
of making friends .
So , children , please , beware of gifts .
Beware of those that offer them .
And beware of those who are only too happy to take them .
GRETEL : Fairy tales have a funny way
of getting into your head .
I don 't remember where I was , or when ,
that I first heard the story
of the Beautiful Child in her little pink cap .
Just feels like I 've always known it .
I wonder how someone gets
their own fairy tale told about them .
And if I 'd even want that .
You have to go through a lot of terrible trouble .
Then most the time , some prince appears
and wakes you up anyway .
But I don 't see any princes around here .
There 's only my little brother .
He follows me wherever I go ,
and I have to share everything with him .
But at least he 's mine .
Why are you wearing that ?
I 'm going to meet with John Stripp .
And his wife , if he has one .
Mother imagines he needs a housekeeper .
But why are your lips so strangely colored ?
( DOG BARKING IN DISTANCE )
( METAL CLANGING IN DISTANCE )
Okay .
If I should ever see so much as a crumb of cake ,
you 'll be the first to know .
Okay ? ( SNORTS )
( INDISTINCT CHATTER )
MASTER STRIPP : Do you read ?
Uh ... No . Though , I am able to bake and launder .
Your father was a farmer , yes ?
GRETEL : Was , yes .
He 's gone ahead to his reward .
Uh , Mother 's alone now , and does what she can .
I should think she can do precious little
till this terrible pestilence is lifted .
Some say the lands are cursed .
MASTER STRIPP : Only with the incompetence of men ,
as so much of everything is .
And really , it 's the whole system that 's so absurd .
I mean , senselessly , we owe crop to some bishop ,
and we 're not even permitted to feed our own ...
You will do well to limit the number of words
that come out of your mouth .
Yes , sir .
Do something nice for a poor , old man , won 't you ?
Try saying " milord " instead .
Yes ...
milord .
That 's a good girl .
I think you 'll find our guests will prefer it .
Now , I have something to ask you .
Have you kept your maidenhood ?
I beg your pardon ?
You may beg all you want ,
but my question remains .
Are you ...
intact ?
( THUNDER CRASHES )
GRETEL : What if I had reached across and slapped him ?
Would my palm have stung with pride ?
Would I have felt nothing ?
MOTHER : Would it have killed you to smile at the man ?
To just say " thank you " ?
( THUNDER RUMBLING )
He didn 't need a housekeeper .
You can 't stay here , Gretel .
GRETEL : Why not ?
Because there isn 't enough room .
This place is too crowded with ghosts .
Hungry ghosts ,
of everything now gone .
Your father 's sits right there .
And mine will be here soon enough .
You shouldn 't talk like that .
You 'll take your brother , and make haste to the convent .
Throw yourself at the boots of the sisters ,
and pray they take you in .
Hansel will never be offered admittance at a convent .
And I would never ask to be admitted .
Then the two of you can start work
digging your sweet , little graves .
( SIGHS )
Gretel .
When you and your brother take up your shovels ...
dig a hole for Mommy , too .
( MOTHER SNORTS )
( SCREAMING ) Be gone !
( GASPS )
Or I 'll hack you into tiny , little pieces .
( THUNDER RUMBLING )
GRETEL : I pulled my brother from his bed ,
and together , we fled the only home we 'd ever known .
The door slammed at our backs ,
and the big , bad world opened up in front of us ...
like a terrible mouth .
Hmm . You ought to have gone with the man in the house .
Quiet about things you don 't know .
Why do you always do that ?
I don 't always do anything . I 'm not a clock .
You make trouble .
You would 've had your own room .
You would 've seen a crumb of cake sooner or later .
Nothing is given without something else
being taken away .
When can we go back to Mother ?
Remember the widow , Hayes ,
who used to give Father eggs before her chickens got sick ?
She lives just up ahead .
Perhaps she can give us a bed .
How do your eyes see that far ?
I don 't have to see things to know that they 're there .
HANSEL : Are you sure a woman lives here ?
GRETEL : I 'm sure a woman used to live here .
HANSEL : Doesn 't smell like a woman lives here .
GRETEL : Quiet .
And be glad for the roof over our heads .
Well , not exactly an iron maiden .
Come on , then .
HANSEL : You think Mother 's all right ?
GRETEL : I think she 's all right
as long as we 're all right .
Gretel ,
will we be all right ?
If I 've got a voice in the matter .
( SHUDDERING )
( SCREAMING )
( MAN GRUNTING )
Brother !
HANSEL : Gretel ! Help ! Get it off me !
- GRETEL : Hey ! - ( MAN SNARLING )
( SCREECHES )
( GROWLING )
Oh , but not really .
( SCREAMING )
- ( ARROW WHIZZES ) - ( GRETEL GASPS )
THE HUNTER : You 've been turned out of your home , I 'll wager .
Set out to fend for yourselves
with only your clothes and your hides ,
which aren 't much .
HANSEL : I have an axe .
Oh .
I must say , it hides very well in your shadow , young man .
I mean I have an axe at home . ( SIGHS )
Be quiet .
THE HUNTER : I 'll be happy to direct you to foresters .
Good people .
Plentiful coin . Food , if you can earn it .
They will hand you a new axe ,
and show you how to make it work like one .
You , girl ,
will learn the ways of the herbs and the earth .
Lest the men of the world find a more obvious use for you .
Pray , sir , what might we offer you in return for the meal ?
I mean , you would 've eaten it if not for us .
I don 't have a taste for rabbit .
What do you want from us , then ?
You have nothing I need or want .
" For kindness is its own reward .
" But cruelty is a self-inflicted wound .
" The wicked earn a living by deception ,
" but the one who plants righteousness
" gathers a true harvest .
" Indeed , those who do what is right
" will live a good life .
" Those who pursue evil will die . "
But everyone dies .
Indeed . But not right now .
Take your fill , and perhaps
you 'll allow me to draw you each a bath .
The boy here is so filthy ,
he could pass for compost
if it not for the whites in his eyes .
( THE HUNTER CHUCKLES )
GRETEL : Is it safe to trust someone
who appears exactly when you need them ?
Or does it feel too much like they 've been lying in wait ,
coiled like a serpent ?
THE HUNTER : Keep west for two full days and nights .
Keep to the path I 've drawn for you ,
and you 'll find what you 're looking for .
Stray from it , and you can expect to meet wolves .
And if you do , don 't stop to talk to them .
They 're very charming and handsome ,
but make terrible conversation .
HANSEL : Why couldn 't we stay
where we were with the huntsman ?
GRETEL : If he 'd wanted children ,
I suspect he would 've made some of his own .
HANSEL : " Made " them ? Out of what ?
Must I explain all of everything ?
HANSEL : But Mother didn 't make us .
We was brought in through her window by birds .
You 're right , Hansel .
What a fool I 've been all this time .
All finished ?
Yes , and I 'm still hungry .
Only the natural result of eating so much .
Oh .
Do you remember Father very much ?
No , not very much .
Tell me the fairy tale again .
The one about the Beautiful Child
with the little pink ...
Not right now .
It 's too scary , and you 'll start
seeing things that aren 't there .
Some things that probably are .
It isn 't scary for me .
And it helps me go to bed .
Gretel , I 'm scared .
GRETEL : ( SOFTLY ) There 's nothing and nobody out there .
BEAUTIFUL CHILD : ( WHISPERS ) Gretel .
( CROW CAWING )
GRETEL : I always try to tell my mother
that I can see things ,
like I was dreaming when I was awake .
But she always told me to keep it to myself ,
and that little girls should never ...
( WOOD CLUNKING IN DISTANCE )
What in hell are you doing ?
Practicing for when we meet the foresters .
And you said " hell . "
Hey !
All this practice is making an unnecessary racket !
I 'm sorry .
I 'm hungry .
I 'm hungrier than you are .
Because you 're a pig .
- You 're a bigger pig . - ( GRETEL CHUCKLES )
You 're right . I am .
( BOTH SNORTING )
HANSEL : When do we eat again ?
( STOMACH GROWLING )
( ECHOES ) Gretel ?
Gretel , I 'm starving .
HANSEL : Looks like a mushroom .
GRETEL : Yes . But they 're as different
from one another as people are .
This one might be unfriendly .
How to tell ?
Suppose we might ask them .
Well , anyhow , here we all are
and pleased to make your acquaintance .
We 've been without food for too long now .
And to be completely frankly honest and open about it ,
we were thinking of ,
very seriously , of supping , well ,
on you .
So tell me if you will , strange little things ,
are you kind , or no ?
What did it say ?
Strange as it might be , I think she said , " Eat me . "
( STOMACH RUMBLING )
( LAUGHING )
( DISTORTED LAUGHTER )
BEAUTIFUL CHILD : Follow me .
( HORSE WHINNIES )
Come and find me .
Follow me , sister .
HANSEL : Gretel ,
is that there ?
GRETEL : If it isn 't , neither are we .
Do you smell that ?
Gretel , it smells of cake !
Hey .
HANSEL : Let go of me !
Gretel , it smells of cake ,
and I 'm unable to resist .
Gretel , I need food .
GRETEL : Stay where I can see you .
HANSEL : They have a slide .
GRETEL : Yet I don 't see any children .
It also smells of bacon , you know .
HANSEL : Look in through the window or something .
Well ?
What is there ?
Only heaven .
HANSEL : What ?
Gretel , look and see !
Hansel .
Brother !
You must be the sister I 've heard so much about .
Careful with that , dear .
I 'd hate for you to start something you can 't stop .
We never intended to steal from you , missus .
" Missus " ? Think I 'm married ?
See you a ball and chain at my heel ?
But tell me how you came to be in my woods ,
and so charmingly unchaperoned .
Our mother has come upon hardship .
Usually the first thing a mother comes upon .
My sister won 't go to the convent .
Be quiet .
WITCH : I very much doubt that a convent is the place
for a girl with action in her bones ,
even if there 's hardly any meat on those action bones .
Aren 't you expecting guests ?
Guests ? I 'd rather have roaches .
Just checking ,
to be sure you 're not crawling with louses
before you put your heads on any pillows of mine .
Ouch !
( SNIFFS )
You 're clean enough .
Now , eat .
And rest .
Beds have already been made up for you .
Thank you .
But really ,
we 'll stop briefly but we must be on our way .
WITCH : Milk ,
good for bones .
A hair here , a hair there .
( CAT PURRING )
( SIGHS ) My eyes too big for my stomach , obviously .
And your mouth is too big for your mouth , obviously .
( STOMACH RUMBLING )
( OWL HOOTING )
( INDISTINCT WHISPERING )
( DISTORTED VOICES )
( WOOD CLUNKING )
BEAUTIFUL CHILD : ( WHISPERING ) My mother , she killed me .
My mother , she ate me .
Oh , what a pretty bird am I.
CHILDREN : No !
( BIRDS CHIRPING )
WITCH : Your breakfast .
No morning beasts for you , my pretty ?
Oh , no , thank you , ma 'am .
She can keep all the world 's vegetables ,
while I eat only meat and grow strong like an ox .
She 'll grow strong enough .
Just as the ox , with his vegetable-made bones ,
pulls the cart and the fat man who sits atop it .
( POT SHATTERS )
Well , another one bites the dust . ( CHUCKLES )
May I not help you with that ?
What 's this , dear ?
Only to say surely in exchange for your generosity ,
I might offer to be the one
out of the two of us to get down on the ground .
Now , that 's a new idea .
I can bake and launder ,
uh , turn down beds ,
or tend to any , um , animals that might need tending .
And I can chop wood .
- He can learn . - Well , I could .
Typically I 'm not in the habit of employing children ,
but in this case it does seem a fair trade .
Only until we set off again
to find a thing more permanent .
We 'll be working with the foresters soon .
Well , it 's beginning to appear
the foresters will have to wait a while .
Finders keepers .
WITCH : The sliding door to your right .
Lyes and vinegars on that shelf .
Soap from animal fat , just there .
And the blade high like this ,
then lay it down easy .
Very good .
Once you 've gotten the hang of it ,
you can move on to the others in the shed .
My , my . Aren 't you handsome .
( SNEEZES )
WITCH : Nothing to sneeze at .
Even with the heat of your blushing ,
you have the onset of a chill .
Here , let me show you something .
Licorice root , garlic , calendula ,
usnea lichen , yarrow flower , milkvetch ,
and finally , cat 's claw .
Ah .
Here .
What ?
You drink it .
( HESITATES ) Oh , I don 't ...
Tomorrow you will be a new girl .
If not tomorrow , then soon enough .
In any case , you will have taken a first step .
The foul smell is only an ugly gatekeeper
in front of the palace of wonders .
Stop with him at the gates , or see what goes on inside .
( GRUNTING )
You 're coming with me !
( PANTS )
Idiot trees .
( SIGHS )
WITCH : You 'll get the hang of it .
Always remember ,
the king is afraid , and he should be .
Because the queen can do whatever she wants .
Gretel ,
it 's naked .
GRETEL : Your go .
- There 's a storm coming . - HANSEL : There isn 't .
Be quiet .
HANSEL : I was out all day .
I know what rain clouds look like , and there was none .
In any case ,
I brought your axe in for you just to be safe .
How 'd you know ?
Because women often know things
they 're not supposed to .
Don 't we , Gretel ?
HANSEL : Gretel 's not a woman .
Oh , no ? And if not ?
What ?
Is she a snake ? A frog ?
A pig ?
( SNORTING )
( THUNDER RUMBLING )
( RAIN PATTERING )
( THUNDER CRASHES )
( THUNDER RUMBLING )
( GRETEL SIGHS )
( DOOR SLIDES )
( CHILD GIGGLES )
CHILD : ( WHISPERS ) Don 't look at us .
Don 't look at us here .
Down in our hole in the ground .
We 've gotten old down here .
Don 't look at us .
( ECHOES ) Don 't look at us here .
Down in the ground .
We 've gotten old down here .
Don 't look at us .
( CHILD CRYING ECHOES IN DISTANCE )
( CHILDREN GIGGLING )
GRETEL : Were the dreams I was having
only the result of too much rich food before bed ?
Were they a message ?
A warning ?
Was I now missing a chance to listen to myself ?
( KNOCKING ECHOES )
( CAT YOWLING )
GRETEL : Hey .
We 'd be wise to leave before outstaying our welcome .
What ?
Leave ?
Yes .
And continue on to the foresters ,
like we said we would .
We 've found work to be done here .
You probably noticed the food .
There 's something wrong here .
But it 's so pleasant .
But tell me what hides behind that pleasantness .
There are things here , bad things .
What bad things ?
The abundance , for one .
What 's that mean ?
It means " too much . "
There 's too much , and it isn 't right .
Where are the animals ?
From where does she draw milk ?
From where does she conjure up her endless parade of cakes ?
There are souls trapped in this house , or under it .
But why do you always see a problem ?
Something behind or under ? Something hidden ?
Because the big , bad world is what it is .
We 're safe now from the world . Isn 't that what you want ?
Perhaps tomorrow you can send me for supplies .
Mother says I have an eye for good produce .
WITCH : That won 't be necessary .
Plums only keep for three days out of season .
And that ham is unsalted . It must be going bad .
And yet , it isn 't .
( THUDS )
Yes !
( CHILD WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY )
( TREES CREAKING )
( CHILDREN SCREAMING ECHOES )
( CHILD CONTINUES WHISPERING )
CHILD : Hansel , Gretel .
( GASPS )
Come across an old one , have you ?
One that 's had too much to drink .
You 'll find another in the cupboard in the hall .
Towards the back .
When you 've found it , let me show you something .
WITCH : The thought in your head is ,
" Go look in the shed . "
You 'll find saws to be sharpened
for the bones of the dead .
The thought in your head is , " Go look in the shed . "
You 'll find saws to be sharpened
for the bones of the dead .
What eats with its teeth , but never feels fed ?
( DOOR CREAKING )
Are you having dreams ?
On some nights .
On some nights , I don 't sleep at all .
WITCH : Awake ,
listening to the woods ?
Good .
The air is swirling with abundance .
One need only reach out and pluck it .
This is your power ,
to see what is hidden and to take it .
A small mind believes only what it can see .
Carves out a little square ,
waits to be taken ,
never wondering what governs its fate .
But we know that we are our fate 's own masters , don 't we ?
Those like me and those like you ,
we commune with the Great Provider .
She gives us the seeds of abundance ,
and we grow them in our garden .
We harvest it , and with it ,
we impart justice .
You say " we , " but I 've not agreed to anything .
It 's not for you to agree or disagree , my pretty .
It 's already inside of you .
You can either stay asleep to it ...
or let it wake up .
( STAFF THUDS )
Now ,
the salve .
I see it likes you .
( CHUCKLES )
( THUDS )
Now , tell it what to do .
" Tell it " ?
You 've talked to things before . I know you have .
What can it do ?
It can do more than just lie there like spilled milk .
( WITCH GASPS )
You decided to wake it up , after all .
But how did it ...
WITCH : Think less , my pretty , and know more .
Go ahead .
It awaits its master .
WITCH : The bones of the dead .
The bones of the dead .
( BRANCHES RUSTLING )
( TREES CREAKING , RUSTLING )
( TREE CREAKING )
( CREAKING CONTINUES )
( CREAKING LOUDLY )
WITCH : Have another bite , won 't you ?
- ( FLY BUZZING ) - I don 't want another bite .
Even if it bit me , I wouldn 't bite it back .
But it 's your favorite , my little champion .
I even stuffed the crust .
HANSEL : And it 'll be here again tomorrow ,
as sure as the sun ,
and with even less explanation .
Quiet . You 're being rude .
Now bite your tongue and eat your food .
( FLY BUZZING )
HANSEL : What do you do with her all day ?
She teaches me .
Things that could save my life ,
that could make my life .
She 's not our mother , you know .
It 's true , she isn 't .
She has much to give .
You wouldn 't understand . There are many gifts here .
You always say there aren 't any gifts in this world .
That nothing is given without something taken away .
So , tell me this ,
what is she taking ?
I 'm scared now ,
and I want to go home .
I wanna see Mother .
We both know there 's nothing there .
But gifts ?
Are you forgetting ?
Forgetting to be afraid of gifts ?
I 'm not .
What about the story ?
" Once upon a time , a girl was born . "
It 's not like that .
But " all in the village agreed
" that she was the most beautiful child . "
You 'd do well to shut your mouth .
" It came to be that she was touched with the gift of ... "
( HANSEL GASPS )
Fall quiet , boy .
For I shall write my own story .
Gretel .
You wanna leave ?
Let me show you how .
Gretel ! Don 't leave me !
Gretel !
BEAUTIFUL CHILD : ( WHISPERS ) Follow me .
( BREATHING SHAKILY )
GRETEL : Surely , that had only been a nightmare .
The desire to be rid of him was very real .
But to send him off alone into the night ,
that could never be true .
( WHISPERS ) Hansel ?
( WOLF HOWLING IN DISTANCE )
He 's out sulking ,
blaming the strength of the trees
for his own weakness .
He 's a little boy .
Even the littlest pebble makes it difficult to travel
once it gets its way into your boot .
You 've taken him on as a burden .
But last night you shrugged it off .
Did I ?
Didn 't you ?
You 're not his mother .
And still , you don 't remember
the last time you couldn 't be sure
of where your little boy could be .
He shouldn 't be off on his own .
Maybe not .
But you definitely should be .
I ought to go to bed ,
to be up with the sun to search for my brother .
An excellent plan .
But I do fear a restless night ahead .
Might you prepare for me something to help me sleep ?
I 'll fix you a sleeper . She always does the trick .
You 'll sleep like a baby ...
If the baby has just got into her mother 's sleepers .
Yes .
Thank you .
WITCH : Careful with a sleeping draft .
A leaf or a twig this way or that ,
you get a very different mixture .
A soup of nightmares .
Well , good night , then .
( RETCHING )
( COUGHING )
( GRETEL SNORTS )
Come on now . This is no place for you .
Come now and look at me .
( LIQUID POURING )
( BLOWS AIR )
( CHILDREN WAILING )
( FLESH SQUELCHING )
GRETEL : It didn 't matter anymore
if I dreamt it or really lived it .
The horror of what I had seen under the house
was proof of what I already knew .
All I could do now was keep calm and play dumb ,
only for long enough to outsmart her .
WITCH : Disturbing night , was it not ?
Did you feel the wind coming down from the hills
rattling all the windows facing east ?
I suppose I didn 't .
Desired result of my sleeping draft , I 'm sure .
You saw there 's fresh milk ?
I saw .
Yum .
Any sign of our little runaway ?
No , none .
Well , I 'll keep a nose and an ear out .
You 're going somewhere ?
It 's not regular that nature calls out to me ,
but when she does , I try to answer .
Mind the kettle , would you ?
Fix me a cup of tea for when I 'm back .
That 'd be nice .
And leave the food out .
Maybe I 'll want to bite something later .
( RETCHING )
CHILDREN : Bless the day if you dare
to desire to be born again .
( DOOR SLIDES OPEN )
WITCH : I 've been thinking ,
maybe it 's for the best that Hansel isn 't with us .
Isn 't ?
He 'll soon come to fear you ,
as all men should if they 're smart .
And fear so easily turns to hatred .
Better that he remember you as you were ,
rather than as you 're meant to be .
With all that you 're showing me ,
will I one day be very powerful ?
You will be .
Will I have mastery and dominion over everything ?
WITCH : Nearly everything .
We must accept our weaknesses .
Have you one ? A vulnerability ?
Only that which has taken a part of me .
Only that which has taken a part of you .
And to you it will be a poison .
And so you must consume it ,
lest it consume you first .
Consume poison ?
How else will one develop an immunity ?
But the thing about poison
is that out of everything in the big , bad world ,
nothing tastes as sweet .
What did you do with my brother ?
I am only moving him out of your way .
He 's all I have in this world .
Say that again and I will turn your tongue into a flower ,
to remind you of how pretty and dumb ,
temporary , you 've chosen to be .
Or you may follow the path that I 've lit for you .
Do whatever you want with me ,
but only if you free him .
I could never do that .
GRETEL : But why not ?
Because that little boy is your poison .
All that is left is to make him delicious .
You can 't .
My dear ,
I can 't remember a time
when there was anything else I cared to do .
I envy you ,
standing at the threshold of your own experience ,
with everything ahead of you .
To be young again .
( INHALES DEEPLY )
A nice balance .
I admire the application .
But more than anything
it leaves me curious as to why ,
why you would try to put me to sleep
when there is so much to be done .
I won 't do what you want me to do .
I 'm nothing like you .
We are made from the same matter ,
the same filth .
Otherwise , how would you know my story
without me having to tell it to you ?
Your story ?
We were given the same gift ,
the same magic ...
just as she was ,
with her little pink cap .
How do you know my s ...
( SNAPS FINGERS )
WITCH : I know that 's your favorite story ,
but you have been telling it wrong .
It 's true ,
she was a most beautiful child ,
and everyone could see that .
But on the inside ,
she was rotten to her core
and as sweet as vinegar .
Even I hated her ,
and I was her mother .
( METAL CLANGING )
Because from me , she took everything .
And would have destroyed me too ,
if I didn 't get rid of her first .
So I gave her back to the darkness
that had made her ,
and thought that would be the end of it .
But I was wrong .
She stayed with me .
In my thoughts , in my dreams , attached to me like my shadow ,
promising me a taste of the powers that she had .
All that was required was for me to be brave
and to trust the darkness .
And I was ,
and I did .
And like she had done ,
I rid myself of all other attachments .
I cleared my plate .
I ate my children .
So hungry was I to realize my own powers ,
I hardly even chewed .
I assumed a disguise of old age
to make myself seem kind and weak .
I built for us a house ,
one with a proper kitchen and a dining room .
( GASPING )
( ECHOES ) I could name them all if ever I had to .
There was a Thomas and an Isabella ,
a darling William
and a precious Elizabeth ,
a Harry and a Sarah ,
a Paul , a Kate .
And now , just for you ,
a Hansel .
Only rid yourself of him and embrace your powers .
Such a sweet boy .
Sweet and plump , and fair .
Where is he ?
Where is my brother ?
WITCH : So stay a while , won 't you ?
Who knows , you might even enjoy it .
( FIRE ROARING )
I only hope you 're hungry .
( THUDS )
Bedtime for you ,
little darling .
Go and kiss your sister good night .
Brother , hear me .
I know you 're in there . I 'm going to get you out .
Even though you are blinded , you 'll see my face again .
That is my forever promise to you .
( GRETEL SNORTS )
YOUNG WITCH : That 's enough .
Now up to bed .
There 's a good boy .
What a world .
( YOUNG WITCH GRUNTING )
Hansel , hold !
( SCREAMING )
( YOUNG WITCH SCREAMING )
Hansel !
( GRUNTS )
( BREATHING HEAVILY )
( BIRDS CHIRPING )
( CAT PURRING )
Gretel .
Quiet now .
You 're all right .
And you will be , just as long as I got a voice in it .
But what about her ?
She doesn 't live here anymore .
Gretel , you 're scared .
What of ?
Of the world ?
No ...
only of myself .
You will always have a part of me , brother .
A part of myself that you have not taken ,
but that I have given to you gladly .
It will go with you when you leave .
When I leave ?
Without you ?
GRETEL : Yes .
The single story that we shared now splits in two ,
and we take forking paths .
Yours will lead you to what you need to find .
Mine will carry me up .
I told him to take good care of you .
He 'll see to it that you arrive safely .
Gretel , you 'll see my face again .
But anyway , where is he taking me ?
GRETEL : Letting him go wasn 't hard to do .
If he 's going to find his way ,
I can 't very well be standing in it ,
just as he shouldn 't stand in mine .
I could see she was right about that at least .
Let him find his own story ,
and his own courage to live it ...
just as I now go on to live mine .
I have my own power to nurture .
I 'll help it to grow ,
and trust that I 'll know what to do with it .
I know that the choice is mine .
I could feed it darkness , or give it plenty of light .
I looked , and I saw ,
and I understood .
The captor now gone and her fires all put out ,
they were free to go ...
and be at peace .
And I was free .
To go and never look back ,
or stay to build something new
on top of everything that had been destroyed .
I knew my path would reveal itself ,
and that all was required for me was to be brave
and to trust myself .
And I am brave .
And I will trust myself .